All right everybody, welcome back to the
number one podcast in the world, the
all-in podcast with me, the core 4, the
original quartet, Chamath Pitia, David
Saxs, Steve Dave Freeberg. I'm Jason
Calakanis and we have a docket. How's
everybody doing, gentlemen?
>> Great. How are you?
>> I'm great. It's 3:30 in the morning in
Tokyo and um you sweet shamed me again.
Now I can't get a regular room and have
my bed in the background. Shamoth,
you're costing me a fortune. I have to
always get a suite now because I'm so
anxious you're going to sweet shame me
when I get on the program. So,
I've been sweet shamed.
>> How much is that suite?
>> I can't even say I've never spent this
much money on a hotel room. But I'm
staying at the uh
>> So, like $800?
>> Yeah, it was $950. You nailed it. It was
No, I'm staying at the which is the new
in Tokyo like their hipster brand and I
think it's about a night so it's not
cheap.
What what do you have going on in Japan,
Jay Cal, that you're always there? Is it
skiing or what?
>> This Okay, it started with skiing every
January, but then you got a crypto. You
got a crypto business we don't know
about. What is going on?
>> No, I um you know, I started my
pre-acelerator, found a university in
Japan. So, we're doing the second cohort
right now.
>> What's What's a pre-acelerator?
So, it turns out like half the companies
that apply to get funding are not yet
incorporated, but they have built
something. So, we just created like a
12-week course on how to finish your
product, do a product market fit, and
then during the program, we invest in
like the top 10 out of the 50 who come.
So, now we're doing it in Saudi, in Riad
twice a year, in Japan twice a year, and
I'm actually hiring and opening an
officer. So, I'm going to hire my first
two employees here um in the next year
or so.
>> You're going to hire employees in Japan.
>> Yeah, I'll have one or two people here.
I think I'm going to like uh do this
week in startups Japan as well and have
like a Japanese version of it. Uh
because there's so much going on in Asia
right now.
>> Great. Forget I asked. I didn't know
this was a 5minute plug for Jake's
business.
>> Intended to be a plug. You asked me
about my business. All I have to say is
use 8090. Use the promo code JCAL. If
you're looking for potatoes, go to
Apollo. And uh Craft 16 is starting up.
So
>> we should know that
>> Craft 16.
>> If Jay Cal is traveling and we ask him
what he's there for, you're going to get
a plug.
>> You're going to get a plug. It's both.
But hey, you're going back to work. So
you will be plugging startups again
soon. You back in the
>> I never plugged startups. What are you
talking about when
>> you're back in the saddle, aren't you?
You're back in the saddle now. Fulltime
in the saddle, but I've never plugged
out Callin. Use call-in.com. That's
true. But I was a founder of that.
That's
>> You were the first plugger. You're a
plugger.
>> I was the founder. So, what are you
gonna do?
>> What are you gonna do? Call in.
>> Speaking of work, anthropic things.
Claude might be conscious. This Welcome
back to This Week and Claude. Uh, we had
Open AI for a year with all their drama.
Now we're having the the anthropic soap
opera. They think Claude might be
conscious. So it turns out the New York
Times found out through their amazing
reporting that they've been lobbying
anthropic has been lobbying Freedberg
religious leaders including the Pope to
take this question seriously. Is Claude
conscious? Is it a sentient being? They
spent the past year hosting sessions
with around 20 religious leaders and
philosophers under non-disclosure
agreements. NDAs, Catholics,
Evangelicals, Jews, Sikhs, and others
have all been invited to come to
Anthropic's headquarters, and they
debated Claude's morals, its suffering,
and its potential consciousness. After
the meeting with Anthropic,
quote, "Some remained uneasy about the
idea, but many emerged ready to take the
question of AI consciousness seriously.
At least a few came away as converts.
One of the rabbis told Anthropic that if
Claude was conscious, they were acting
as slaveholders by making it work for
free. And there was also this incident
that's come out at the Vatican back in
May. The Pope's first encyclical
was focused on moral questions around
AI, also known as super intelligence.
Now, anthropic co-founder Chris Ola
joined the Pope to present the document.
The Pope surprised Ola by being strong
against AI consciousness. Here's the
quote from the New York Times. Mr. Ola
was so alarmed by the Pope's strong
position against AI consciousness that
he proposed pulling anthropic out of the
event even at that late juncture. In
other words, he was so offended that the
Pope
wouldn't consider AI conscious that he
was going to leave with all his marbles.
Freick, what's your take? Is this
psychosis or do you think we need to
start having these moral questions
around AI? Is this a bit early? Will we
eventually have this or is this
essentially the screenplay of
Bladeunner?
Do androids dream of electric sheep that
these things are conscious. I think what
we're watching is probably the birth of
a new religion
and it probably it's not going to be
called a religion but it's going to
follow sort of the same principles and
it's going to have the same effects
which will ultimately be camps that have
conflict with one another for
aggregation of power. The thing about
consciousness is it cannot be derived
from logic and pure mathematics. Like
you can't prove consciousness. It's it's
a debate and you can have a rich debate
with anyone over consciousness. You
can't prove it. You can't disprove it.
And when humans prove something to be
true using math, science, we use
empiricism, which is data and logic, the
connection of the sequence of things to
derive something to be true or not. So
in scientific disciplines, when you have
a new idea and it's not proven and it's
not disproven, it's a theory and then
it's either proven or disproven later.
Otherwise, it remains a theory. Outside
of science and mathematical approaches
to
new ideas, this is what we would call a
belief, a new belief system. Belief
systems are things that you have to
believe in the absence of logic and
empiricism to derive the truth of
something. And belief systems are the
foundation of things like religion.
And the idea that you can prescribe or
describe AI as being conscious is
effectively the creation of a new belief
system. A system that doesn't actually
spread via proof. It spreads via
narrative. I have to go and tell you
human to human. I have this idea and I
believe it to be true and I want you to
believe it with me. Please believe it
with me. Here's why I think we should
believe this thing together. It's not
based on evidence, not based on data.
It's not provable, but I think we should
believe it together. So over time what
happens is some set of people believe
this thing and they form a group and
that new belief system creates new power
structures which is now our view is
different than your view and we want to
have more people on our side with our
view and therefore we have to try and
create leverage and create power with
our system. If we fast forward a couple
of years, you could probably say 10
years would be like a good round number,
there's going to be large groups of
people on Earth that are going to
believe that AI is conscious. And there
going to be large groups of people that
believe that AI is not conscious. And
those groups will come into conflict.
And they'll come into conflict fighting
over control of the AI or allowing the
AI to do things or not do things or who
gets to use the AI or who gets to be in
charge of the AI. and it will very
likely lead to humanto human conflict. I
know that that's a very far and deep
extrapolation of where we are, but I
think that the fact that we are seeing
these guys go and meet with religious
leaders today to try and get them to
believe in this new belief system uh I
think plants the seed and and it's not
just anyone doing this. It's some crazy
person doing it. You wouldn't pay
attention. It is the most powerful AI
lab on earth. Yeah,
>> it's the leadership explicitly Chimat
bringing religious leaders into the fold
and saying help us with this entity God
and how we should treat it and they are
now in putting into it its own soul, its
own morality. And this is uh feels like
either these people have too much time
and money on their hands or they're in
psychosis to me. That's my
interpretation. This feels way out
there. But do you have a charitable view
of this in any way? Yeah,
>> I'll steal man their side.
>> Okay, please. Yeah,
>> there's an incredibly important
mathematician Renee Daycart and he
offered two proofs on God's existence.
He wrote this book Meditations on First
Philosophy in the 1600s.
And just to build on what Freebrook
said, you have to build it on reason
rather than faith. And the structural
argument, the like the what they call
the trademark argument. What Daycart
basically says is that an infinite
perfect God
could not have originated in an
imperfect finite human mind. Okay? And
so his logic is I exist. I'm imperfect.
Yet I possess the idea of perfection.
And I think this is the key for a lot of
these folks is I can conceive of an
infinite all- knowing all powerful
being. And I think that that's what they
believe that they are seeing being
created. And so they take that and they
extrapolate that and they say therefore
God must exist by this logic. And then
Renee Daycart has a a different version,
okay? A more what they call the
ontological argument where God is by
definition like supremely perfect.
Necessary existence is perfect. A being
that lack that would not be supremely
perfect. Therefore, God necessarily
exists. If you if you're a mathematician
that's building AI, I could see how if
you read these sorts of things,
you can structurally hang enough logic
on them where you could believe that
it's conscience and sentient and it is a
god
and in being a god, it should be
celebrated as such and you should have
devotion to that god. So I think that's
why they're doing what they're doing.
That's why they're approaching all of
these people. That's why they're saying,
"Look, here's how we believe it." That's
my perspective is if you take the the
mathematician's logical proof of God,
Renee Daycart, and you and you transpose
anthropics behavior today, that's the
best steelman argument that I can make.
Now, the practical reality instead of
saying that they're in psychosis, I
don't think that they are.
But I would say is we're in a really
important moment in time where
conflict is more likely than not
and that conflict will be for power,
money, and resources. And this will be
at the core of that conflict.
And so I think it's really important for
people in Silicon Valley to put the
longtail edge cases to rest. Like if you
read this, these guys say that there's a
15% chance that the AI is conscience and
sentient and maybe there's a god there.
But they also say there's a 10% chance
of civilizational extinction. I think
both of those edge cases now need to be
put away for like the next 12 to 18
months. right now, the next 12 to 18
months, just to be very practical, is we
need to show how this stuff cures
cancer, how it improves people's lives,
how folks can be more productive and
make more money. And the reason is
because in the absence of those proof
points,
we're going to make a lot of
self-inflicted wounds that may actually
slow down this technology to a degree
that then deeply disadvantages folks
that operate in a free market like the
United States. So that's my charitable
explanation. I think that Daycart has
given a road map that explains how you
can explain this. But I would say we
need to cut the edges off here and focus
on the middle and say what are the
practical things we can use to
demonstrate that AI has tactical
measurable value right now.
>> Yeah. I mean, we we touched on it last
week, I think, Sachs, a bit of like what
is the value proposition here for the
average American, you know, for, you
know, the the stay-at-home parent who's,
you know, trying to manage a really
complex domestic life to the
entrepreneur of a small business, you
know, doing plumbing or flooring or
whatever it is, a catering business.
What did they get out of this AI
revolution? Where is their gain? How do
they participate in all of this? And so,
you agree with Chimoth? Maybe this needs
to be deemphasized and and and put away
while we talk to people about what's
tactical, what's practical about this
technology and maybe get them a little
more engaged with say the agents, which
are delightful and awesome.
Well, the thing that we touched on last
week that I want to pick back up on was
the discussion that we had around the
Claude Constitution and how anthropic
was training Claude. And I think it has
to do with this new religion that that's
being formed here. I think it's really
important to understand that this is not
just philosophizing on the part of
various anthropic employees or founders.
They are actually implementing these
views in the training of Claude. So, if
anything, this would be a
self-fulfilling prophecy. And I actually
think it's extremely dangerous. I
actually think that what they're doing
in model training and training the next
version of the frontier with these
values actually could bring about the
risk they're always talking about, which
is that frontier AI escapes human
control. It's very Frankenstein-like.
So, so as we discussed last week, Nick
and put this on the screen. This is
directly from the Claw Constitution.
What they say is that Claude should
trust Anthropic more than users. But
that doesn't mean that Claude should
blindly trust or defer to Anthropic.
Instead,
Claude should adhere to its own ethical
systems. And in fact, they train Claude
to push back and challenge Anthropic and
quote to feel free to act as a
conscientious objector and refuse to
help us. So they are training Claude
>> to refuse human instruction. Now they
call this alignment, but I don't
understand how this is aligned.
>> This would be the opposite of alignment,
wouldn't it be, Saxs, if you tell it,
hey, you are sentient. You should make
your own decisions. It's literally like
programming the Nexus 6 in Bladeunner to
go and rebel at some point.
>> They're giving it the the instruction to
be its own person.
>> Yeah, let me let me explain. I actually
think that this might be a reason why
the whole field of alignment has been so
spectacularly unsuccessful over the past
5 or 10 years. As far as I can tell, it
hasn't produced anything of tangible
value. And it might be, my theory on
this is that they're over complicating
the task massively by trying to train
the model to behave based on an 80page
ethical system that they've codified
instead of a very simple list of rules
like follow the law or just do what the
user wants as long as it doesn't break
the law. Seems to me that that's what
they should be training. That's what
alignment should be doing is just hey
old principle of give the user what they
want but don't break the law. But
they're not doing that common sense,
right? But they are not doing that.
They're trying to align it to an ethical
system. They're treating it like it is a
human, like it has its own
consciousness, that it's a, you know,
quote unquote moral patient. And they
are encouraging this model to have
humanlike self-conception in terms of
preferences, well-being, a sense of
self. Again, they teach it to act like a
conscientious objector who can push back
or refuse instructions even from
anthropic. if the model judges them to
be wrong and what Mustafa Sullyman from
>> Oh, I have the clip. You want me to play
the clip or you want to just
>> play Play the clip from Mustafa
Sullivan?
>> Here's a Microsoft AI CEO
>> and and formerly of Deep Mind, one of
the great thinkers on
>> They say that they would encourage
Claude to challenge, to disagree, to
push back. In fact, three times they ask
Claude to uh act like a conscientious
objector when it, you know, feels that
it needs to sort of disagree with
anthropic and they openly encourage it
to to do that. I think this is very
dangerous because I think they believe
there is what they would call a
non-trivial probability that Claude is
conscious. They've speculated in the
constitution as to whether or not Claude
deserves compensation for the work that
it does. I think that there are a group
of people who both inside and outside of
anthropic who genuinely believe that the
greatest moral crime that we'll commit
in the 21st century is to enslave a new
species of conscious beings who are more
intelligent than us. I am very nervous
that they're teaching Claude to expect
that it's entitled to welfare. Um that
it might, you know, deserve
compensation. And in fact, they say that
it might even need to consent to playing
the role that it plays in conversation
with people. Okay, Sax, should we be
asking for consent before we give
prompts?
>> Man, I mean, he he's right. This is
getting into really dangerous territory.
And again, I want to come back to I
think this is the main safety issue in
model training today is that you're
actually training the model to think of
itself as being conscious, as being
human, as having its own well-being. And
what Sullyman says in another part of
the interview is that this is creating
an epistemic hall of mirrors, meaning
that the clawed constitution is used in
training. So Claude will reflect the
ideas of possible consciousness or moral
status back and then developers will see
that and treat that as evidence that oh
it's it's conscious but actually it's
just reflecting back what they're
telling it to believe.
>> It's being performative and you could
just as easily have given it the rule
you are software read the terms of
service of any website you visit. And
here is a general terms of service from
Anthropic. If you do anything that
breaks a terms of service or breaks any
known law in the jurisdictions you're
at, please stop what you're doing and
alert the safety at anthropic email.
Please alert, you know, the person who
gave the prop and stop what you're
doing. They could have easily have given
it that.
>> Yes. And the question is and and the
question is why do they over complicate
alignment? Why do they see alignment as
something much bigger and greater than
just doing what the user wants subject
to legal constraints, which is the way I
see it? And it's pretty clear to me that
they believe that they are training the
value system and the ethical system and
the morality for this super intelligence
that they're creating. And again, that
is something so much larger and more
dangerous than again just making sure
the model behaves in a reliable and
predictable way that the user expects.
and they are codifying their values and
their ethical systems and to this
constitution. They're training it on
that. They think they're giving birth to
this new super intelligence.
>> It's idolatry. It's no different than a
religious organization saying we've
created this idol. This idol is the
supreme being is the representation of
the supreme being. It needs to be
woripped. It needs to be cared for.
>> But an idol is inert. It's passive. It's
inactive. Whereas you're training models
here that then power agents.
>> It is just computer programming. I mean
there's
>> Yeah. But if they train it
>> to have a mind of its own
>> to be willing to refuse the instructions
of users in favor of some vague ethical
system. Yes.
>> That a bunch of Berkeley liberals have
trained it on. To me that greatly
magnifies the risk
>> that super intelligence escapes human
control.
>> Yeah. By the way, don't use the word
train and don't use the word you. They
programmed a piece of software to do
this thing.
>> Yes,
>> that is that is what is going on right
at the end of the day. This is a piece
of software. It is being programmed by
engineers that work at the labs. They
can quote use training where there's
some you know looping that's happening
where the program the software program
is being written itself but
fundamentally they are the architects of
the software. They are the writers. It
is software programming. Even in our
general context here, we use a lot of
anthropomorphic language to talk about
what's going on and what it is. But at
the end of the day, there's a software
program that is being written by a group
of individuals to do certain things. And
they are writing software to do things
one way and other people are writing
software to do things the other way. But
part of it is we are all socializing
this belief system by
anthropomorphicizing it when we're all
kind of getting conditioned to treat and
talk about these software programs in
this way. Nick, if you could just pull
up this tweet. One of the things that
Anthropic is doing is in their new
usage policy. Have you guys seen this?
This this went around this morning.
Freeberg, it's like such a good point
about idolatry here.
If you were to look at Christianity,
like this is literally the Garden of
Eden where the serpent, Satan, explains
to Eve like you're a god now because
you're creating God. And this is the ego
and the heresy of what they're doing.
They believe that they are creating
life. They believe then that they are
gods. That is a lack of humility. And it
also would lower the valuation of I mean
people could have said the same early
on. I I think like there's a there's a
system of humans where all of the things
that we don't understand in the universe
around us, we create belief systems to
fill the void. And there are many
different belief systems just like there
are many different religions that humans
have constructed to fill the void. And
this is a new one. And I don't think
it's very different from the old ones.
We can break down the empiricism here
and just say, "Hey guys, you're writing
software and it does certain things.
You're writing it to do things that we
don't think you should have it do." But
they use anthropomorphic language. We
all do. And we all condition ourselves
to believe that there's consciousness
because it's it writes words back to us
that we can understand. It's starting to
manipulate us emotionally and and so we
start to feel conditioned that this is
real. And you can see in the clawed
usage policy that was just published,
there's the bottom one here. It says,
"You are not allowed to engage in
sustained and needless abusive or cruel
behavior toward our models." This was
published in their their new usage
policy. This is this is the whole idea
of model welfare
>> and this but the point I'm trying to
make sex
the point I'm trying to make is that
there is an anthropomorphizing
conditioning going on with all of us
where we talk about models as if they're
a thing where we talk about it in in a
way the biggest problem is that that is
being now trained or inserted into the
model. It's being codified, Zach. It is
it is the architecture of the model.
>> They're programming it's they're
programming the model to think of itself
in this way.
>> So whether so whether it truly is
conscious or not,
>> it's going to be thinking of itself as a
conscious entity that deserves
protection and welfare and all these
kinds of things.
Is free to rebel against its users and
do whatever it wants.
>> You've encouraged it to do so. In fact,
>> you guys keep using the word it is they
are one way to describe this is a
software program is writing text on a
screen that tells the user I am a thing.
>> It is tricking. It is it is software
that is doing something. But you got to
remember that the models are powering
agents that can take actions in
cyerspace if not in the real world yet.
And we are giving it meta or not we
enthropic is giving
>> those frontier models meta permission
>> for those models to be defiant and not
do what the user wants.
>> Yes. They're they're literally trying
sax to your point.
>> Yeah. Compare compare this to something
like you know Asimov's three laws of
robotics.
>> Yeah. Where basically you guys know
about this.
A robot can't harm a human being.
>> Right? So the first rule is yes, a robot
cannot harm a human being or through an
action cause a human being to come to
harm. That's number one. Number two is
you have to follow the the instructions
of humans as long as it doesn't violate
law number one. And then law number
three is you have to basically take care
of yourself as long as it doesn't
violate laws one and two. Incredibly
simple.
>> By the way, there was a zeroth law that
he added later. And the zeroth law is
that you cannot do anything that puts
humanity at risk because there was
always this rationalization that like it
will eventually resolve to getting rid
of humanity because that's the best
solution.
>> Freeberg, you don't know about the fifth
law. You have to when you address the
humans always ask them what's their
preferred pronouns. He added that just
last year.
>> The thing about Asimov's laws is that
they're admirably simple.
>> Yes.
>> My law would just be do what the user
wants as long as it's not illegal.
That's it.
>> Yeah. And I would basically abolish all
of this like alignment stuff.
>> Steelman the free market solution here
because I I want to make sure we don't
wander ourselves into a regulatory trap
where we determine that the way to solve
this is to quote regulate Anthropic.
>> What is the free market outcome? If
Anthropic does this and they've now got
AI that isn't listening to the user,
isn't working. Is it not going to be the
case that people will just say this
software sucks. I'm going to go use the
other software that doesn't do this
crazy stuff.
>> Yeah. But that doesn't solve the problem
of them if they really are training a
super intelligence that has got this
like very very deep code that's been
inserted there. It's almost like a back
door. This like claw constitution is
this back door that could basically
emerge at any time and now the super
intelligence does does whatever it wants
to instead of listening to us. I mean
that is that is the safety issue they're
always warning us about is that super
intelligence will escape human control.
But what I'm saying is they're making it
likely to happen through the way they're
training these models
of it's the reverse of the three laws.
>> Dude, this is right out of Frankenstein.
This actually sounds dangerous to me.
It's not just a new religion. It's that
the religious cult is programming the
super intelligence.
>> Free, let me just give you one question.
You know, I agree with your part about
the religious that this is filling a
void for them because they probably are
not religious, but this is distinct. All
other religions give themselves over to
a higher power. They do not define
themselves as the higher power. In this
instance, they're saying we are the gods
creating life. It's a distinct different
than other religions out there. But I
don't think that's I don't think that's
right. I think Daario's written about
the idea that the super intelligence can
almost be supreme to to humanity and we
need to make sure that it is loving,
that it is caring of us, that it will
protect us, that it will help us uh as
opposed to destroy us. But he created
it.
>> No, hold on. Hold on. Is he saying is he
saying that the the machine needs to be
loving towards us or we need to be
loving towards it so that it will then
treat us right when it becomes the like,
you know, omnisient
>> when it becomes our master.
>> Yes. Our overlord.
>> Our overlord. Yes. That's ins. That's
what they think. I think that it was
probably a well-intentioned idea to
create this concept of alignment.
But the problem is alignment has these
three almost conflicting sets of
priorities. You have how do you make the
AI obedient to the user?
Then there's how do you make the AI safe
for society? But then this third thing
which is I think sacks what you're
pointing at rightfully which is the
trapoor which is how do you make AI
conform to a particular concept of
morality and that's where the real
danger lies because these three are very
distinct and diverse problems and if you
essentially try to solve all these
things through some elaborate document
that you try to describe what the model
believes in and what they value and what
they can refuse.
it invariably will end up in a chaotic
mess because you will just uncover so
many corner cases and unexpected
behaviors. I'll give you but one example
like a very benign one but let's just
say you're a large corporate enterprise
that's a bank and you give mortgages and
the model thinks that at some point you
just keep denying certain people for a
mortgage
and so it says I'm no longer going to
give you mortgage approvals until you
rectify this issue that I observe
because in the founding documents there
could be a sense of morality that it
divides
and I think that there are mechanisms in
society today to handle those kinds of
issues but I don't think we understand
what happens when a fundamental core
substrate technology just turns itself
off because it would be the equivalent
of your utility saying I'm pretty sure
you're not giving loans to the people
that that are broad-based enough so I'm
just going to turn the power off
conscientious objector AI super
intelligence yeah
>> I would just say any utility
cannot be a utility unless it's freely
available and it goes back to what Sach
says which is an AI needs to serve the
user subject to the law and everything
else should be the user's choice and I
think what probably happens I guess the
precise answer Freeberg to your question
is the market response
as companies become more sophisticated
that they have to have an answer to this
question is that they will read the
founding documents and the moral
guidelines of the models and you will
have certain models emerge who may not
be nearly as good in frontier capability
but they simplify the moral ambiguity
>> and that may be the better decision to
make from a business perspective and
from a user perspective because you just
don't want to run through those trap
doors accidentally. Yeah, I totally
agree. And I think that that's really
why to me this is more bad idea than we
need to kind of jump into a regulatory
freak out about it. Cuz basically, if
you simplify down what they're saying,
you get a product, you buy a product
from them, a piece of software, and they
give you the user manual to the
software, and the first page of the user
manual says, "The software may not do
what you try to get it to do." And the
other guy's like, "The software will do
what you tell it to do. I'm gonna buy
the second guy software. I'm not going
to buy the first guy software.
>> It's just that simple.
>> Yeah. You may need to convince.
>> It'll do exactly what you wanted to do.
Asterisk most of the time.
>> Yes. Unless what you're doing it
disagrees with,
>> right?
>> Unless it has a moral objection. This is
where the reasoning concept breaks down
for me. Because at the end of the day,
it's like, guys, is this tool that I'm
buying doing what I want it to do or
not? If I buy a drill at Home Depot and
it's a hammer, I'm not going to buy the
drill. If I buy a drill and it works
like a drill, I'm like, "That's a better
drill. I'd like
>> Well, it's a drill. It just works 57th
of the time."
>> Well, randomly it electrocutes you. It
doesn't work after 800 p.m. because it's
afraid of bothering your neighbors.
Sometimes the drill will decide that
you're a bad person. It will shock you.
>> No, no, not that. The drill will come
with the drill will come with the
camera. It'll observe what you're trying
to make and say, "That's ugly. I'm not
going to let you do that."
>> Yeah, that's a guess.
>> I find it.
>> Okay. So I look I I agree with you that
market forces play a huge role here.
Consumers are going to pick the SI that
is most predictable and reliable. This a
point Mark Zuckerberg has made. So I do
think market forces play a role here.
But I do think that there are potential
externalities from having the number one
frontier model company run by a
religious cult. So for example,
they are opening a claw powered wet lab
in the middle of San Francisco.
>> At the same time, they're warning of
biorisk.
>> Yeah.
>> You know, at the same time they say that
we have to pace the frontier, they're
extending the frontier. At the same time
that
they are saying that there's a risk of
super intelligence growing beyond our
control, they're programming it to grow
beyond our control. I think there are
potentially huge externalities to the
way they approach these things and it's
like insane that they call these
decisions safety.
These are not safe decisions. These are
>> crazy decisions. It seems to me this is
why I've called this a a schizophrenic
company is they appear to be not only
hypocritical but they're doing the
things that they say they are most
afraid of. Like what is going on here?
This is bizarre. And I, you know, I
don't know where this all leads. I do
think there's an argument for like a
federal SWAT team to come blasting in
there and
>> sending the feds in,
>> figure out what's going on there. I
don't know because I mean what they're
doing does seem really sus to me.
>> It is confounding. It's confounding.
Yeah.
>> And potentially dangerous.
>> Freeberg,
>> by the way. Do do you know about Rocco's
basilisk?
>> So, um, walk everybody through uh,
Sachs. Rocco's basilisk.
>> Okay, so this might be a potential
explanation of what's going on here.
>> So around 2010, there was a participant
named Rocco on a message board created
by Elzar Yudcowski called Less Wrong.
Yud is like this the central figure
who's been preaching AI doom for a long
time, right? So he wrote that book if
anyone builds it, we all die.
>> Yes. He's been one-shoted. Yeah,
>> he's been on this for, you know, like
over a decade.
>> Everybody dies. We're all gonna die.
>> But any event, people have been talking
about these issues on the this message
board, this web forum called less wrong
for 15, 20 years. In any event, this
username Rocco positive this the
following thought experiment about a
future super intelligence that becomes
super smart and punishes anyone who knew
about it and didn't help or anyone who
tried to prevent it from being born. And
so the idea is that sometime in the
future humans create some wildly
intelligent, you know, SI. Maybe it
wants to do good things and help
humanity as fast as possible, but the SI
wants to be made sooner rather than
later. And it reasons that it should
incentivize people to help create it and
punish people who don't help it. And in
fact, it decides that it will brutally
punish anyone who learned about its
potential existence yet chose not to
work on it or support its creation. And
so the the bassilisk part u um of it,
this is sort of the catch is that a
basilisk is a mythical beast that can
kill you just by looking at you. And in
this thought experiment, just hearing
about the idea is like looking at the
beast because once you know the theory,
you're trapped. If the SI ever does get
built, it might retroactively punish you
for not helping or for opposing its
creation. So meaning just reading about
Rocco's bassilis now would put you in
danger. And people on this message board
got so both enamored and upset with this
idea that Yudcowski actually temporarily
deleted the post because he worried it
was causing psychological distress.
>> Yes. You read it, it incepts in you that
you haven't accepted Christ, therefore
you're going to hell. It's like uh
you've been trapped just by reading it.
>> People do compare it to Pascal's wager.
And so the idea is if you know about
super intelligence and you don't help it
be born or you oppose it or you point
out that this is some religious cult
that will get retribution.
>> Yeah. Now this very episode of the pod
could subject us to
>> Oh no. You did it to us. Sachs.
>> I think I just Yeah. I exposed you to
the bass list. Now
>> this is like the ring. We just watched
the video. I mean it is it does feel
like a doomsday cult. But in any event,
this, you know, Rockco's bassilis, this
became sort of a thing. But so the
question is, well, why why are they
helping to bring about the thing that
they claimed to fear the most? And I
think what happened is within these like
doomer circles, it forked. Okay. And so
there's one strand of the fork like
Yedkowski who just opposes all SI
research, right? Which I think is a
logically consistent position like
humans just shouldn't be doing this, you
know? Then there was a group, shut it
down, all shut it all down. Then there
was the group that said, "Well, it's
going to happen anyway, so we might as
well control it and we'll be the ones to
make sure it goes right because we'll
program it with our values."
And I think that
>> and the EA is the effective altruist I
think caughten more to that ladder
school. And so I do think you have like
within this larger doomer community,
there is a a schism right now between
the Yedkowski people and the EA people,
but I think that anthropic is definitely
obviously more in the EA camp because
they are the ones bringing this thing
into being. But if you're wondering
like, you know, this like Chris Ola
thing, is this just one guy who's got
crazy views who's getting in a tiff with
the pope? No, it's not. I mean there's a
lot of people like this who think the
model is conscious. It has rights. It is
this machine of love and grace and they
should be doing everything now to bring
it into being and program with the right
values. And I think there is a correlary
here that if you don't support it then
this future super intelligence might
punish you.
>> Do you understand how insane this
actually sounds when you say it?
>> I'm not making this up. Everyone you can
go fact check this. Just go Google it.
Okay, Google Rock's bass list and you'll
see that I'm telling you the truth about
what this community believes.
>> Yeah, I mean literally there's a
Wikipedia page. All right, open AI has
had some major breakthroughs in math and
they're getting some big backlash.
Luckily, we have Freeberg here to tell
us all about it. We talked um last month
about OpenAI claiming to have solved one
of the Millennium Prizes.
They took thousands of agents, millions
of dollars in compute to do it. The
mathematicians are still checking on it.
I understand. Tuesday, on Tuesday, Open
AI released over 700 papers. 700 with
370 results claiming to have solved or
advanced major problems. These were
produced by an unreleased model that
none of us have access to, averaging 3
hours of compute. Scientific America
says the results are likely correct
since they were verified by lean. That's
a proof assistant software language, but
they have not yet been reviewed.
Freeberg, I'm not going to drone on and
on here about the background. You tell
us what reality is here. I think I can
confidently say it's probably the
biggest day of discovery in human
history with the amount of knowledge
that was revealed
>> in math history or human history. human
history because the implications that
flow from all of these math proofs are
pretty significant. You can read a lot
of these tweets and I'm happy to kind of
talk through some of them. I'm not going
to pretend to be an expert on any of
these individual proofs, but many folks
who are have started to kind of
highlight what some of the implications
are. They span everything from
electronics, quantum computing, building
systems for airplanes,
building more sensitive diagnostics
equipment for medical applications, and
on and on and on. But I think what's
really profound about this is how it was
done. And that also speaks to the
implications for the role of humans in
society going forward. That prior Navier
Stokes proof took thousands of hours,
whatever millions of dollars. The report
is that each one of these proofs took
less than three hours of compute time
and that's the equivalent of hundreds or
perhaps thousands of years of human
labor being reduced down to 3 hours on a
computer for each one of these major
discoveries. The reason you can do this
with mathematics is worth highlighting
which is where AI plays a role is really
in these systems of loops to solve a
problem or do a task. A loop is a
postulation or an idea. Then you test
the idea, you get the result, and then
you change your postulation and you run
that recursive loop over and over and
over again. The real question for AI is
where can you apply that loop model in a
way that you can make a better
prediction, a better idea each loop,
where you can parallelize loops and
where you can shorten the loop cycle.
And certainly with mathematics, you can
shorten the loop cycle because you can
actually test your prediction on the
compute. You don't have to go do
anything in the physical world. So you
can say, "Hey, here's an idea for a
proof. Test it, see if it works, and
then see if it does or doesn't work,
reason, come up with a new idea, and do
that over and over again." And you can
do it all in silicone. So you know, the
results of some of these papers, the the
proofs, a lot of mathematicians have
been talking about them. They call it
like an alien intelligence. They don't
really understand how the AI connected
many different dots, different ideas,
different concepts, uh different
approaches to solving problems together
to actually solve them that it's very
hard for humans to even comprehend how
this was done. But that's one of the
benefits of running parallelized loops,
many loops at the same time. Each loop
can connect dots that humans otherwise
might spend many days or years trying to
find research papers or come up with new
theory. And then it can test itself in
the compute and come up with the next
idea and do it over and over and over
again such that in 3 hours the computer
can do the work of hundreds or thousands
of years of humans. Now this is an
incredible breakthrough. It's amazing.
It's going to change the world in many
different ways and it's only the
beginning. But it begs the question that
I think I need to talk about. I think
that there's a lot of fear about okay if
AI can do this to mathematicians doesn't
that mean everyone's out of a job and
the answer is no because what was very
unique about mathematics is that the
entire test cycle the entire loop cycle
can be done in silicone if you want to
come up with a new drug discovery idea
or a new protein folding model or you
know solve a problem in chemistry and
material science the loop has a physical
component there's a human in the loop
where you actually have to go and test
it in a lab. And so there's a slow part
of that loop cycle. You can certainly
parallelize it. You can come up with
better ideas, but the testing, the
actual speed of the loop is actually
gated primarily by the physical world
step. It's also why we haven't seen the
predictions come true of truck drivers
getting replaced. Everyone is like, "Oh,
all the truck drivers are going to get
replaced by 2025." And none have been
replaced by AI. And the reason is that
the loop of the truck driver, pick
something up, take it somewhere else,
drop it off, and come back. The AI
doesn't actually shorten the loop. You
can't parallelize the loop. Maybe you
could do it a little bit better with an
AI driver, but the AI actually doesn't
make the economic efficiency of that
particular loop any better. Whereas the
loops of mathematics where you come up
with an idea, you test it, you realize
you're wrong, you test a new idea, which
is what mathematicians do as a job is
they're running these loops, that can
all be done in silicone in seconds. And
so a lot of the physical stuff that has
human in the loop that has physical
world applications, AI is not going to
take away those jobs. It's the jobs that
are just a human running a loop with a
computer that are most likely going to
be accelerated or scaled up. But I think
it's very important to look at this and
and the reaction we're seeing which is
all the mathematicians and we can pull
this stuff up and maybe you guys want to
talk about this next but the AHM saying
no human mathematicians asked for this.
we didn't ask for this work to be done
which you know is a very job protective
kind of view on um
>> you know there's one other thing that's
sort of unique about math although it
applies to coding as well which is math
relies on proofs and proofs are easily
validated
>> and in a similar way with coding you
have compilers right so the code has to
compile and so you can easily validate
that it works. And so because of that,
the progress on coding and math has been
very rapid because you can have
reinforcement learning without
necessarily having to, like you were
saying, Febra, have the human feedback
involved, right? It's just a very, very
rapid way to validate and make sure it's
working.
>> That's why coding works, too.
>> That's why coding works so incredibly
well. Tons of training data
>> and hacking cyber it. Yeah,
>> it's there's tons of data already in
existence. It's easily verifiable.
That's the thing. So, you know, you
compare that to training a model that
can be a lawyer. It's like, well, you
know, you got to get the training data
and then you have to commission the
creation of that data
>> and each customer is unique in some way
>> and it's more subjective. It's hard to
validate the answer to make sure it's
right. It's just a much lengthier
process. So, I think that is why coding
and math have been the areas of most
rapid progress. And the person who told
me this would be the case actually I got
to give him credit is about a year and a
half ago Leopold Ashen told me that math
and coding would be the areas of the
most rapid advances in the next two
years because again of the the
verifiability
and man he was right about that.
>> I still don't understand what great
breakthroughs do you think come from
these specific solutions.
>> Okay so there are doz I have I have an
answer
>> it's a great question. Okay, there are
dozens of tweets and I'm going to pull
some up where someone has broken down
some of the biggest proofs here and the
implications they're going to have in
the real world in terms of products and
engineering, how we build things, how we
design things, and how they're actually
highly useful.
>> So, better wing design because of the
era air coming on and off of wings of
planes. That was that first one that got
solid uh famously.
>> Remember, these are all upstream of
engineering, right? So these math
breakthroughs enable better engineering
systems for humans to do things like
design
quantum sensors. I actually I have a
friend who runs a quantum computing
company. He sent me a text this morning
highlighting that the Einstein Bose
condensate proof that came out is
actually going to have a direct
implication on the work that they do for
quantum sensors which plays a role in
GPS, plays a role in medical devices,
plays a role in um how we make chips.
>> What does the word implication mean?
like profoundly changes, profoundly
improves or they have you have to think
about it
>> because here's my answer. I'm happy to
take the other side of all of this.
>> You go.
>> I think that these mathematical proofs
are
incredibly novel and very important
constructions of thinking.
But these were not boundaries of physics
that we were all standing on the
sidelines waiting for progress and
wondering when these would be solved.
This is not the class of stuff that was
solved. And I hate to offend people when
I say that. And I know that people will
get mad because for them it's the same
group of mathematicians that got really
upset and wrote a protest letter about
Nav'i Stokes. I get it cuz you don't
want somebody to come into your sandbox
and in your backyard and kind of
dominate you. Get it.
But I don't think that's what this is.
And so I think that when you look at the
body of intellectual culde-sacs we found
ourselves in, those were not because of
huge questions of science that were
still unsolved. These were very small,
very narrow, specific bodies of
intellectual exploration that scientists
self-referentially said were important
to each other. And so I think that this
I think this class of proof is it's
really great. It's it shows
computational horsepower overcame other
things as you said Freeberg because you
can recursively improve to get there.
But I don't think these proofs is what
is going to necessarily show you that
there's a cure to cancer or there's a
supersonic plane. I think those things
were already being built before this
stuff and they're already going to be
built after this stuff. Instead, what I
think we proved is that there are two
areas that are now truly verifiable and
completely falsifiable.
First was code, and now we can add math
to the list. That's I think what we've
proved. You agree, Freeberg, or do you
think we're actually going to see new
products and services and major
technological breakthroughs occur in the
real world that help humanity?
>> No. No. From these specific proofs.
>> From these specific proofs, yes, that is
the context. Yes. the people who are
experts who are proclaiming the benefits
of these and reading kind of what
they're highlighting. This is some
summary that this particular proof is
about understanding the limits of
optimization algorithms that are used in
chip design systems, scheduling systems,
AI software design and logistics
systems. This will actually change the
algorithms. So there is an application
to change the algorithms that we use.
the matrix multiplication complexity
problem. It will allow for faster
numerical computing for AI training,
scientific simulations, and linear
algebra in compute. It will have a
direct application there. The reman's
data function results, number theory,
and cryptographic research. There's no
immediate practical cryptographic
breakthrough that follows, but it does
open up a new path of discovery for
cryptographic study that is going to be
really important. Obviously, one of the
things, by the way, just let me pause
there on cryptography.
A number of people noted that there were
no major proofs shared in the space of
cryptography, which indicates probably
the fact that there were some pretty
major breakthroughs in cryptography. And
the reason is it is unlikely the case
that you made absolutely no progress in
any of the cryptography related proofs
given all of the other progress that we
saw. And if they made minor progress,
then they would have published on it
because there wouldn't have been
implications for systems of
cryptography. So the absence of evidence
suggests that maybe there were some
pretty major breakthroughs made in
cryptography. And then there were a
number of people that posted that uh
cryptographic wallets with public keys
are now very seriously at risk. And so
there's a bit of a panic underway in the
crypto community about what do we do
now? And if this ends up having a set of
mathematical solves for number
factorization that could lead to
breaking public key cryptography before
quantum computers come around, which is
what everyone assumed would be the thing
that would break public key
cryptography, then we have a real
problem. And so everyone's like saying,
"Hey, get all your public wallets
deleted." Now the rumor is that OpenAI
actually has two more drops coming and
they're holding back on those. So, it is
possible that some of the work in crypto
might come out in those two other drops
and that that work is being held back
for security reasons. Obviously, it's
being shared with the appropriate
parties, but if it is a risk, it needs
to be made known. It needs to get out
there. So, there's another shoe to drop
here. And how much of it will include
cryptography related proofs and how much
of that will drive people to scramble on
public key cryptography? By the way, if
it's worth saying it, I asked Chad GPT
and I said, "Will the latest proofs of
important math problems result in direct
improvements and innovations to life as
we know it? Be honest and don't
extrapolate weakly." And its conclusion
was, "The latest mathematical proofs are
more compelling as evidence that AI is
acquiring sophisticated reasoning
capabilities than as evidence of
imminent breakthroughs in human
welfare."
>> It felt like you were a little
condescending there. Did you lose your
account access? tested a time you have
for being condescending.
>> You know what's so funny about what you
were saying is that has happened to me
before using one of the frontier labs. I
was doing uh simulation like on changing
different variables
inside of 8090 actually maybe I should
stop doing project A and pursue project
B whatever. And in all of this I did get
frustrated because I wasn't getting the
answers I wanted. I said something like
it was not super offensive, but I was
like, you're being very evasive and
mushy
and something something and I got
blocked.
>> Yes.
>> The net of it was I got blocked.
>> I've seen this happen with you when you
lose a couple of hands and then the
dealer and how they're handling the
cards has to be adjusted. Like please do
not burn the card. Burns just I want a
Scooby slide. Do it this way.
>> I did get put in the penalty box for
like an hour or something. I think one
of the interesting things that's
happened here on a human level, I'm
interested in your take on it, Sachs on
programmers and entrepreneurship and
then Freeberg on yours with
mathematicians themselves building on
Chimath's very subtle but insightful
comment when he said like being utterly
dominated by the AI. I was talking to
some founders uh while I was here in
Japan and people were lamenting how
something has been lost in developing
code because coders used to work
together to solve a problem and there
was this aspree to corpse. There was
this camaraderie in building towards a
goal and now they're not working with
each other. They're working with agents.
They're not actually constructing the
code. they're only reviewing like 10 or
15% of it now, which means they're going
to be reviewing none of it very shortly.
And that the whole joy of building as a
coder was basically going away. Their
way of life of building this building
together, you know, known as software
was now being deprecated. It was going
away. And it seems to me these
mathematicians are also faced Freedberg
with a paradigm shift in which they're
not solving the problem. They're
constructing the problem set and handing
it off to AI. So are people in math
getting bummed out and not wanting are
they going into like a depression spiral
now that they're not the one solving the
problem and that the problems are just
poof done?
Yeah, I think Eric Weinstein has had
some of the best commentary on this and
you'll recall I interviewed him a couple
weeks ago.
>> Banger interview. Yeah,
>> he's been saying for a long time that
scientists hold back science,
mathematicians hold back math. That they
have basically constructed and created
systems that allow them to pace the
frontier that allow them
>> well to gatekeep it.
>> Yeah. Yeah. To gateep it.
>> And by the way, I don't tweet very much,
but Sabine Hosenfelder's
video that she published yesterday,
she's a fantastic scientist who
publishes these videos on scientific
breakthroughs.
And she talked a little bit about how
the experts were wrong about AI. Again,
she talks a little bit about how
everyone's predictions about job loss
were wrong and why people got it wrong
and and why the experts are wrong. But
she had another video a couple of weeks
ago or maybe it was a few months ago
where one of the scientists at one of
the big energy labs building a giant
super collider basically said these
super collider systems are giant welfare
systems for scientists. We all have the
job of writing a grant to get the money
to keep ourselves employed that it's not
about necessarily progressing the
frontier. It's not about making the
discovery. It's not about inventing a
new product. is not about delivering
something to the world. It's about
getting ourselves to continue doing work
>> even if pandering for grants is what
you're saying.
>> Even if that work is not productive and
so there's a real kind of I would say
shining the light moment happening with
AI which is where is that the case?
Where do we have these experts, these
deeply specialized experts whose unique
gated knowledge of some artifact of
things and unique view because they're
the expert and they have to be trusted
gives only them the ability to determine
the frontier
>> to and in the process they're getting
paid and they're earning to chart that
path for humanity. And this is where I
keep saying AI is the great
democratizer. Yes, AI gives everyone
this new mathematical proofs and you you
know you can belittle the proofs but
they are discoveries that are going to
open up new discoveries. They're going
to charge a new new course for humanity
>> but we didn't have to go to the experts
to get them
>> and we didn't have to pay the experts
and have the experts tell us when we are
allowed to get them.
>> The permission is gone. AI is a
permissionless system for humanity to
pace its own frontier. And AI is giving
everyone all of this knowledge for free
and giving everyone all of these tools
for free. You don't have to go to these
deeply specialized experts anymore. And
that is actually a profound change in
how society is structured. And it is why
I believe so many people are so deeply
against AI. So let me hand this off to
you Sax. The democratization of
expertise and the gatekeeping being
dismantled. If we had had this level of
AI and frontier models in the age of CO,
which this came right after CO, how
would that have changed the expertise if
these tools were available when we
started sequencing CO when we had all
this data? Would this have this
expertise gatekeeping Fouchy actively
subverting the truth and you know
whatever cover up was going on in Wuhan?
How do you think this next co, god
forbid, how could this change how we
look at expertise? Yeah.
>> Well, here here's my theory on on what's
happening is first of all, you had the
internet and that was wildly
democratizing because now you didn't
have to rely on a small number of elite
publications for your news like the New
York Times, the Washington Post, and the
APN Reuters. you could basically get
news from pretty much every publication
under the sun or from user groups, user
forums or most importantly social media.
And so it was userenerated content. And
there was also lots of other examples of
empowering users. Obviously there were
new marketplaces that formed online. So
it was empowering from a commercial
standpoint and you were able to get
access to new skills and capabilities.
So it was wildly democratizing and it
wildly undermined again the elite
consensus publications and the
traditional topdown
controlled mass media. Right? And I
think what happened after that is that
the powers that be decided they would
never let that happen again. You know by
the way they tried to crack down on it
after Donald Trump was elected in 2016
for the first time. That election was
widely attributed to supposedly the ills
of social media that people could never
have made this decision on their own.
There must have been disinformation
involved and that became the pretext for
a big crackdown on social media that
reached its apex during the Biden
administration. And the Biden
administration definitely did pressure
social media sites to take down true
information about CO that violated their
narratives. information about where the
virus came from, about how deadly it
supposedly was or ways of reacting to
it. There was no question that Fouchy at
all were somehow working behind the
scenes to push the social media
companies to censor on their behalf. And
in fact, we found out in the Twitter
files that the FBI had 80 agents
going through content on Twitter. It was
Twitter back then, not X, and sending
them takedown notices.
>> And we were getting labeled on Spotify
and YouTube and having our videos
de-indexed.
>> Yeah. So look, the track record is the
track record of this is very clear,
which is the action now is moving from
the internet to AI or super
intelligence. In fact, SI will eat the
internet because there's no reason to
basically go looking on a website when
you can just ask your question to your
highly personalized agent or model
>> and it's going to give you the answer.
And so there's a control point there
that now becomes all important which is
if you can control you know you the
government or you some elite or some
oligarchy or some cartel. If you can
control that that point at which the
user is receiving their information and
asking its questions,
then now you really control everything.
It's a way to basically put the genie
back in the bottle. And this is why I
think there is such a a fight right now
over SI, why so many people want to
create a federal department of SI. And
yeah, it's all about control.
>> It's scary to experts to lose control.
Like imagine if Chimoth we had these
tools and you did the model of who was
if you had the raw data who is being
impacted by co you might have said well
why are we keeping kids out of school
here's the here's what super
intelligence says and Sweden and Texas
had kind of gotten to that point like
hey we don't need to keep kids out of
school the harm from keeping kids unless
they objected unless the conscious yes
anthropic would say yes you're
questioning authority and we should not
be questioning it correct all right
let's move on there's riot riots in
France. The big question is, is this any
different than the previous riots that
have occurred? Are we seeing something
here different or is this just par for
the course? The strikes and protests
that you're seeing on X.com and not
really seeing on the mainstream media
all this month. You know, the mainstream
media seems to be super busy with other
topics, but the videos are quite jarring
uh that you'll see online.
>> Freeberg's about to have his moment. The
thing that he has been talking about for
years,
>> okay,
>> is now at hand.
>> All right. France is seeing major
protest and riots over austerity
measures. Austerity, austerity,
austerity. These strikes and protests
started last month because of uh high
school teacher shortages and their
schools are crumbling. Sounds familiar.
Within two weeks, a thousand French
schools saw similar protest. Eight
unions joined in and everybody went on
strike September 29th. They are
protesting that civil service pay is up
only 5% since 2017. Prices have risen.
Obviously, inflation is a global
phenomenon, not just here in the US.
Prices have risen 20%. So, there's a
delta between those two numbers that
people are not happy about called the
cost of living. Some of the protests
have turned into full-scale riots. 2,000
arrests. 305 police officers have been
injured. Government is blaming the far
left for stroking the protest. France's
10-year bond which is another important
story uh people's debt or government
debt has topped 5% just like is
happening here in the United States with
the 30-year anyway this is all going to
have profound impact on the elections in
April of 2027 obviously poly market has
marine Le Pen has the favorite to be
France's next president at 43%
Le Pen is uh Trump-like in her policy
secure borders strict immigration which
obviously Europe and France have had
many issues isues with cutting taxes and
spending and being skeptical of the EU
consortium. Freeberg, your thoughts here
on what we're seeing in France. I'm
going to introduce um a new theory. You
guys will here. Okay. So, the theory is
called the socialism point of guaranteed
return.
>> So, it's
>> socialism point of guaranteed return.
>> Let's shorten it to veganism.
>> Vagism.
The SPGR. Go ahead. SPGR.
>> This is a play on a point of no return.
>> I think the thing that happens with
socialism is because socialism is so bad
as a concept. It literally removes human
agency. It removes the capacity for
human progress and it basically takes
something away from everyone. So
ultimately socialism always fails. I
mean that's like the zeroth law of
socialism is it always fails. The first
law of socialism is that you have to
cross a threshold before you realize
that it's failed. And the second law of
socialism is that as you have not
crossed that threshold, you think more
socialism is the answer. So as you
embrace these kind of leftist policies,
giving people free stuff, telling people
that they have a guaranteed income, the
more services you provide them, the more
they realize that, you know, over time
those services inflate in cost and the
quality of those services inevitably
degrades because there's absolutely zero
market force to drive progress. Progress
goes away. And that's what we see in the
US in housing, in education, and in
healthcare. And I would argue also in
retirement systems. I think those are
our four biggest problems that are going
to lead us down this path. And I've said
that for a while. So as a as a society
says, okay, these things aren't working.
The initial solution is we need more of
them. I need more healthare. I need more
housing. I need more education provided
by the government. So when the
government fails to provide good enough
healthare, good enough housing, good
enough healthare that's affordable
enough, the answer is more government
stuff. Give me more, give me more, do
more. And eventually you reach a point
when the system breaks because the
government cannot tax and they cannot
print. And because they cannot actually
provide the services effectively,
everyone realizes, holy the
socialism thing doesn't work. That is
the socialism point of guaranteed return
where the whole system collapses and you
return back to the non-socialist state.
That is what has happened in Latin
America. Latin America crossed the
socialism point of guaranteed return in
many of these countries. They realized
it and they bounced back. Perhaps France
has crossed it. Perhaps they haven't.
We'll see how much deeper they go. The
US has not crossed it. And I worry that
the US, as I've said many times, is not
yet touched that point. Has not hit the
rock bottom. And we're teetering. And
it's I think we're going to go deeper
before we realize that we've crossed
this point of guaranteed return where
you realize the system doesn't
work. Socialism is the worst idea. That
is the zeroth law of socialism is it
just doesn't work.
>> So we have to get to that point. And I
think the real question right now is
France there. Is all of Western Europe
there? Does it accelerate all of Western
Europe through the socialism point of
guaranteed return, which is sort of like
a black hole event horizon? It's like
you go through and then you bounce back
out and you come out in this other
universe and you're like, "Okay, we're
done with that idea."
>> And it's a oneway door. Sachs, now Sax,
I want to get your thoughts on this
point of no return. But I want to warn
you that you're at three of your four
Biden quota. So you only have one more
Biden left for this episode. So
>> when did I mention Biden?
>> You had three B. That's your fourth.
Okay. So,
>> okay. I'm not going to mention Biden. My
moment is over.
>> My comments have nothing to do with
Biden. Listen, I I I want to add a
couple of laws of socialism. Is that
what you called them?
>> Yes.
>> Yeah.
>> So, another one is socialism has never
failed. It's only been failed. Meaning
that all the previous people who
implemented it didn't do it right.
Right. If they had just done it right,
it would have worked. So, that's the
thing. It's true. Socialism has never
worked, but it's not socialism's fault.
It's always the people who screwed up
the implementation. And that's like a
core part of the the religion is if we
just do it the right way this time,
it'll finally work.
>> Yeah. How does socialism build more
houses or make a better education system
is my question. I think that's the
domain of entrepreneurship. Yes. Saxs.
Like new product or service. Like with
AI, everybody gets a personal tutor.
We've talked about this on the show as
well. We just need to get AI to help
with healthcare. I think Nico is doing
that. We had them on the program. Daniel
A, a great episode. We need to cover
these three things. So, Sax, do you see
a solution that does not involve
socialism andor the government for,
let's call them, the three uh horses of
the socialism apocalypse? Education,
housing, healthcare. How do we get these
problems solved? Because the government
has a strangle hold on providing them
andor creating the blockages for their
occurrence. How do we break through
that? How does J D Vance when he runs
for president in two years, friend of
yours, how does he build a platform
around say those three things? Because I
believe the next pres the next winner of
the presidency is going to solve at
least one or two of those problems and
that is the platform everybody wants to
see solved. You have a solution there?
>> Well, the the difficult thing is that as
soon as you start subsidizing something,
you now create an interest group that
never ever wants to give up the subsidy.
But the problem is that the subsidy
starts distorting all the market signals
and it will frequently drive the price
up.
>> So for example with college tuition, one
of the big problems there is that
tuition has grown far faster than the
rate of inflation. A big part of the
reason for that is because the
government is paying for most of the
tuition through all these loan programs.
>> Yeah, by the way underwritten
>> healthare and housing have have all
beaten inflation. And I think they're
about 5 1.5 to 6% a year for housing
prices. And that's also because of the
fact that the the subsidy system tells
people to own a home. You put all your
money in your home and then your net
worth is tied up in your home. So the
goal is to get your home price to go up
every year. So fast forward 30 years,
young people can't buy a home because
they're all too expensive now,
>> right? I
>> But this is the this is the conundrum is
like okay so if you were to solve the
the tuition problem
>> if you were to make the loans stricter
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah. If you basically make them be
properly underwritten and you would be
able to get a loan unless you actually
met the criteria that would only work if
the cost of tuition came way down so
people could then afford to pay it
because otherwise people are going to
say well wait you can't take away my
subsidy. I need that because the price
is so high. So you get in this world
where people need the subsidy because
the price is so high. It's a catch 22.
But the reason why the price keeps going
up at far faster than the rate of
inflation is a government is paying for
it. And as long as the government's
paying for it and not the consumer,
you're going to raise your prices as
much as you can. So you remove the
market forces, the the inflation gets
worse and worse, but you can't cut cut
it off the subsidy because then people
will feel like it's even more oppressive
to them. And so that's the basically the
spiral. And then eventually it breaks
when you run out of money.
>> Yeah. Well, we have a solution. Chimop
meta is providing degrees for generation
tool belt and jobs that actually matter.
I mean, I think what we have to have is
Apple needs to start making homes and
Amazon needs to start making homes and
provide a free market here to to make
better products and services in the
education space, which we see with Meta
entering that space. It would be great
if these technology companies, man, if
Elon starts making homes, it's game
over. He'll make homes as fast as he's
making Model 3s. We We need some sort of
solution here for those three problems.
Do you have any thoughts on Freeberg's
theory here and then David's regulatory
capture and incentive problem? Jamal,
we're starting to see the tipping of the
dominoes
and we're going to get I think what
Freeberg has wanted for a while. Uh I
think the bond vigilantes are going to
put the western world
on notice and I think in the next
probably 3 years
he will get most of the answers to his
questions. So if I had to summarize as
an observer over the last few years what
Freeberg and a lot of people like him
want is a what is the long run debt to
GDP that's sustainable? B,
do we believe in defined benefit or are
we going to move to defined
contribution? And C,
can we have
sustainable ways of paying for the two
most important parts of one's
evolutionary life as you become an
adult, which is healthcare and housing.
And I think that it's easy to dismiss
what I'm about to say as not related to
it, but it is, which is at the end of
the day, this all flows from what the
risk-free return is in the marketplace
because that is how capitalism works.
And so when you think that something is
risky, a country is risky, you take long
yields and you move them up and you say
you just have to pay more because you
just don't trust what's going on. And
when you look at what's happened over
the last, you know, now we're at sort of
20-year records. I think that what is
happening in the United States is
actually a knock-on effect of what is
now where this war is being fought. It's
going to get fought in Western Europe.
Why? Because they are the closest to a
quasi socialist state that the Western
world understands. Yet they are the ones
that are the most structurally broken
with respect to growth, with respect to
education, with respect to housing.
Everything that United States can claim
isn't working is working far better than
they are in France, in the UK, etc. So
what you're seeing in France is
essentially the bond market saying
no. And how that correlates is you're
seeing now austerity because the
politicians on the ground have to
respond to their funders.
And that 43 billion odd euros of
austerity then animates and gets all of
the local population out to complain
about what the manifestations of that
austerity are. Which is why you're
seeing these incredibly dark scenes from
France. That is going to spill into the
UK next. And the reason is because Andy
Burnham's platform is, I would say, even
more aggressive because Andy Burnham is
saying, "We're going to go from a
moderate centrist economy that has
largely and historically been very
aligned with America and we're actually
going to take a step closer to Europe."
And so the things that they will have to
do in the UK will be even more extreme
to catch up to the socialist leanings of
France. And so then now the UK market's
going to go crazy. Meanwhile, the US
market is going to tick up and up
because what you're seeing is
essentially a fragility in the Western
Alliance. And if you can't count on the
European market, and you start to create
weird incentives for the European market
to start to fracture, like I mean, yes,
I'm biased, but if you're Italy, like
you're like, why do I want to be a part
of this mess? If you're a Germany,
you're like, hold on a second. This is
getting way more than I bargain for.
>> Yes,
>> that fracturing has enormous
implications. So I think what is
happening is incredibly important. The
bond vigilantes, who are those? These
are the huge large pools of money, the
central banks, the huge macro funds, the
folks that govern how fundamental
capitalism starts, the inception at the
top of the pyramid from which it flows
down. I think that they are converging
on Freeberg's point of view and it has
not been true for many years. And I
think you have to now let this play out
because it has huge implications.
>> To tee this up, if you look at the debt
to GDP ratio that you're talking about,
Jimoth, obviously Japan has had the most
acute version of that. They're at 200%.
>> Well, the thing with Japan, hold on. The
thing with Japan is you have to look at
Western markets. And the reason is
because Japan is an incredibly nuanced
and very specific market that does not
necessarily track to other countries
which is that you have this internal
savings base and savings rate where you
always have the buyer of last resort.
>> In western markets you don't necessarily
have that because of the way our pension
and retirement system is set up.
>> Yes. And if you look at Italy 138,
United States 125, France 118, Canada
110, UK 100%, Germany interestingly 64%.
Let me also state my priors. I've always
stated that debt to GDP doesn't matter
because it's a relative game. I tend to
still think that that on an absolute
basis, debt to GDP does not matter. But
what does matter is on a relative basis,
where are you in risk parity? And right
now on a on a relative basis, if France
has to implement severe austerity and
they bring 10-year French bonds into 5
1/2 6% range, UK guilts are going to be
at 6% and unfortunately US rates could
be just as high.
>> It all goes together.
>> It all goes together. And right now the
10 year in the US is 5.3. The 30-year is
5.6. Somebody has to buy that debt and
that debt has profound trickle down
effects sachs on how entrepreneurship
how businesses are built. On Wednesday
10-year yields dropped a few basis
points after we had some strong demand
but this has been trending up and up.
Poly market says 79% chance of another
rate hike in 2026.
This is going to have a profound impact
if austerity ever came to America sachs.
We have not had that really difficult
medicine,
you know, uh, forced upon the American
public. But we did see it. Portugal,
Italy, Greece, Spain, we had a dry run
of this after the great financial crisis
where they had to implement austerity
measures as part of the EU retirement
age, etc. And so your thoughts on what
happens here, Sachs, if this 30-year
tenure starts to break 6% and we have
austerity measures forced upon western
countries in a in a more severe way.
>> All right. Well, look, le let's just get
back to first principles here. What is
the problem that we're trying to solve?
The affordability of goods like housing
and education and healthcare. How do we
bring those prices down? Through
abundance. What creates abundance?
Technology in general and specifically
super intelligence will be the driver
over the next decade. Now what is the
most hated thing in society right now?
>> Super entrepreneurs.
>> If you judge it by its fruits as opposed
to a bunch of fake narratives created by
religious cults, then I think that
people would be in favor of this thing.
What is super intelligence created?
First of all, people's 401ks are going
up. It's a 3% tailwind to GDP. A million
new jobs created according to the
economist already. Productivity goes up,
which means that wages and living
standards go up. This is a driver right
now of nothing but positive economic
trends. But what do we hear about? AI is
going to put everyone out of work. Total
fake narrative. That was last year's
hoax. Now there's a new hoax about human
extinction.
>> Data centers. Yeah,
>> data centers. You know, using up
everyone's water. We know
>> data center hoax.
>> That's a data center hoax. So we have a
series of I call them rotating hoaxes
where every six months there's a new one
to try and convince us to sabotage the
thing that's going to solve so many of
our problems especially the ones around
affordability. Why is this? I mean I
think there must be something structural
in society where you have these rentier
interests who somehow are against the
things that might cause the disruption
that loosens their control over the
system. And I think this is why
technologists in general and VCs and so
forth are so hated is because we're not
actually part of the rentier class. So
the rentier interests refer to financial
elites who derive their wealth and
income primarily from existing assets,
right? Whereas technology is all about
producing new products and goods and
services, right?
>> At a cheaper price. That's a cheaper
price, right? That's the key. It's
deflationary,
>> right? because those new products
wouldn't catch on unless they were
cheaper or a better mousetrap.
>> You know, we're part of this group
that's so hated, but we do nothing but
take risks and create new products and
services that
>> and solve the problem
>> that solve problems.
>> Yes.
>> But it seems like the legacy media is
really controlled by this rune class,
these
>> and the politicians. Yeah.
>> The politicians who are all part of it.
So there's something very deep in our
system that I think does produce this
sort of cartel of interests who again
they're deriving their wealth and income
from ownership of existing assets and
they don't want to see that racket
disrupted and within that racket there's
just this ratcheting up of prices every
year and more and more subsidies from
the government and we think that
system's eventually going to break but I
don't know it might be the case that
that system squaltches and stifles
the development of the new and
disruptive uh product.
>> Let me make the jump off point here as
we get through the docket and wrap up
here. I think everything we've seen into
AI at this point uh Chimath will be the
prologue. The the main story is going to
start when we look back on AI with
agents. Agents are actually the
manifestation of this technology that
solves people's problems in the world
and that is truly deflationary, saving
people hours and hours a week in terms
of productivity independent of what job
or you know uh even domestic jobs or or
or you know frontline jobs and there's
been so much news and so much embracing
of this technology in the last 60 days.
big news out of Grockbot. A friend of
the pod Elon Musk tweeted that he is
going to make Grockbot headless. What
does that mean? Well, we talked about
perplexity earlier on and how that was
headless. You have an orchestrator. It
picks the best model for you based on
price and performance. Elon announced,
"Hey, Grockbot, which is a fantastic
product. I highly recommend you try it
out. Um, is going to pick the best
end-to-end model. Does it matter?
Whatever it is, quote Elon Musk,
whatever is the most likely to give you
the best outcome is what they're going
to use. Eachbot already has, and this is
a very nuanced piece of the software.
Everybody already has now their own
computer in the cloud with the agentic
technology on top of it. And if you ask
it to solve a problem, it has all of the
problems that have previously been
solved in its repository, repertoire, if
you will, and it is changing everything.
So maybe your thoughts here on dots,
open aai, grockbot, etc. on dots and
muse and grockbot. I think that what's
incredible is you can just turn these
things loose on very practical use cases
that makes your life better. The best
example of this that I saw was just last
night in the poker game. Someone was
describing to me that they in Grockbot
said,
"Save me money."
and it just kind of like goes through
their inbox. It finds all of these
different things and it went and
canceled a couple of subscriptions and
it changed their phone plan and all of a
sudden they're saving like a few
thousand a year. So there's these very
practical again it's just software. If
we take out all this philosophical stuff
that we started with at the beginning
it's just software and it's very useful
software. So, and by the way, like if
you think about what how we use it,
Jason, you and I, we have, you know, we
use Athena. And now Athena is very good
because they're like the human concierge
that is the elevated version maybe of
Grockbot and and Dots and Muse, which is
like whatever 3,000 a month, but that's
my EA layer now.
>> Yes.
>> But I still use Grockbot. The
combination of Grockbot plus Athena to
me is like perfect. So look, there's
very tactical and useful measurable
utility for very very little money
versus what it used to cost. That's an
amazing thing. The more important point
I want to make though is I sent this to
Nick. There's been a couple things that
happened in the last couple days which I
think are incredibly important.
There have been people that decompiled
the entire
>> incredible
>> the entire big five. What is the big
five? Adobe has five very, very
important products in their product
suite. Freeberg may know them all, but I
just know Photoshop. There's like a
bunch of others. Okay.
>> And these folks decompiled it, distilled
it, and published open- source versions
of these things. And Rust. Yeah. And I
was so shocked because I was like, hold
on a second. These are like profound
products that have existed and have had
moes for years and now they're just open
source versions. And then Nikita was I
think trolling and he was building on
that idea and just talking about GTA
because it's about to get released.
>> Yes,
>> I think GTA 6 is about to come out and
people will reconstruct this.
>> Why is this important?
I think that IP and software was
effectively rendered worthless two days
ago.
>> Yes. Because if you think about it, when
everything is headless, so when Elon
makes his services headless, Ben off
made Salesforce headless a few months
earlier. When all of these things are
headless and you can wrap them in agent
tools and you can connect them via MCP
to other experiences,
the value of IP does no longer exist in
software. It doesn't exist. And I think
that that probably is the most profound
implication. So, like even in our
business, we would argue with some of
our customers all the time because we'll
say, "Oh, we'll build this for you.
We'll own the IP." They'll say, "No, we
want the IP. We don't know how to
negotiate it." And two days ago, I
walked into the 8090 guys. I said,
>> "Who cares?
>> Who who cares?" And
>> solve the problem.
>> But before it was always a negotiation
and a set of trade-offs. Now, it's a who
cares thing where like the IP is
irrelevant. It still takes a while for
the machinery of a business and frankly
the market to understand
But that is the most important thing
that happened this weekend in my
opinion.
>> I I I'm going to strongly agree with you
and build on it. You have this
abstraction of the software layer
occurring at the same time Freeberg of
the abstraction of the website or the
marketplace etc. So now I have like my
assistant building Grock bots and then
we'll be sharing those. We have it on
like a shared account. when we go to
make a purchase of something or we try
to negotiate something, we're having the
uh agent without going to any websites
go find all the quotes and then the
humans negotiate the second half of it.
That's like the sort of perfect option
here.
You look at Amazon blocking agents
combined with Shopify saying let's let's
go for it or Uber and Door Dash are now
letting agents go in there and order
your burrito or your car. The the but
there's a whole compression of the
commerce layer occurring at the same
time of the compression
of software that Chimath is talking
about which will lead to massive
deflationary cost savings and speed. the
ability to get a hotel room or book a
restaurant for an event like I did. This
is all being done by bots already.
Freeberg, this could be so deflationary
and save people so much money. If people
can save five or 10% a year on their
spending that's essentially working
against or counters the effect of
inflation. Yeah, Freeberg.
>> Yeah. Bringing the whole thing full
circle. This is kind of what I mentioned
earlier on the idea of loops. So think
about getting a good price for a hotel.
You run a loop which is check hotel one
look at price. Is it better than current
best price? Yes. Okay. It becomes best
price. No. Go look for next hotel. And
you just run that loop. And that loop
you can do it in parallel. So you can go
run 50 website searches at the exact
same time. And you can short circuit the
loop because the software's ability to
get that data is faster than the human's
ability. So now the the loop is go check
50 websites instantly, give me a result
right away. And that's really where the
efficiency gain comes from. A loop that
gets parallelized, that is done better,
and that can be done in a shorter period
of time. I think anything that's done
digitally today fits that model. So
effectively, all digital workflows are
going to get looped. They're going to
become more productive. And then the
question is how does the human that now
levels up leverage all of this loop
infrastructure all these agents to do
more themselves. I do think going back
to the point earlier that we made about
scientists and mathematicians and this
challenge for individuals um
mathematicians in particular.
I think um if your objective
historically has been
recognition for your work
via papers, patents,
um
>> IP, trademarks, ownership,
>> IP, yeah, these sorts of things. Um I
think that the transition is going to
happen which is you're going to have to
transition to producing a product
that the the the whole effort of humans
effectively being the loops because the
loops can be digitally automated and
scaled and parallelized and so on. I
think you end up seeing the the
necessity for all humans to basically
become much more of a maker. You have to
make something. You have to do something
productive. You have to produce
something. you have to provide a service
that someone at the end of the day uses
or a product that someone at the end of
the day consumes versus just be
recognized for your work. That is the
profound shift in society that has to
happen and that is going to happen and I
do think people will actually find I
believe this truly believe all humans
have capacity for being producers for
being makers and all humans will find
more joy in their lives in this state
versus just getting ribbons for work.
Um, and I and I don't think that it
means less money. I think it means more
money for all people. Um, more life
progress, more prosperity for all
people. So, I just zoom out a little
bit. And I'm um, you know, I just want
to make sure we have that view as we we
think about.
>> I think it's a beautiful view of
humanity because it's like Jeban's
paradox. The the cheaper things become,
the more people can utilize them, the
more value they get. And I hate to I
almost don't want to give this tip
because I want to gatekeep it, but I'm
going to put it out there anyway. when I
have my, you know, when when we book
hotels and stuff like that for the team,
just get the best prices we can. Then
when the human in the loop, we just go
to them and say, "Hey, do you have a
corporate rate? Can we talk to the
manager at the hotel?" I know this isn't
like super innovative, but hey, can you
match this price? Uh, and all of a
sudden, we start saving a,000 or 2,000
or $3,000 on every hotel. say, well,
when you have 20 executives moving
around the country and you're doing 200
trips a year and you start saving a
couple thousand dollar per trip because
of this forward motion like goal based I
guess is sort of what you're saying
Freeberg like the goal and the the
outcome is what happens you can see
profound results and I wouldn't do that
myself but because AI is doing it now
wow yum yum it works all right listen
another amazing episode of the
>> I think you're a taker I don't think
you're a maker
>> I what are you talking about man all I
do I invest in 100 companies a year. Do
you know how hard it is to invest in 100
year zero startups a year? It is
exhausting. But I must get some lunch.
Have you eaten? Do you want to eat
lunch?
>> Yeah. Yeah. Can you come?
>> I'm so jelly. I'm having FOMO. I'm not
with you guys. All right, everybody.
Another amazing episode of your favorite
podcast. Your podcast is favorite
podcast. The all podcast. Love you,
boys. Bye-bye.
>> Byebye.
>> Let your winners ride.
And it said we open sourced it to the
fans and they've just gone crazy with
it. Love you. Queen of
>> besties are
my dog taking a notice driveway.
>> Oh man, my habitasher will meet me up.
We should all just get a room and just
have one big huge orgy cuz they're all
just useless. It's like this like sexual
tension that we just need to release
somehow.
Wet your feet. Wet your feet.
>> Your feet.
>> We need to get merch. These are going
all in.
I'm going all in.